An Inventory of the Andrew Meier papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Andrew Meier papers
1917-2007
2010C16
Hoover Institution Archives
14 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (6.2 linear feet)
The collection primarily consists of research materials for Andrew Meier's book The Lost Spy: An American in Stalin's Secret Service (New York, 2008). This research material includes correspondence and notes; photocopies of correspondence and of genealogical and biographical data; photocopies of investigative, consular and other government documents; and printed matter. The bulk of the research materials directly relate to Soviet espionage in the United States and elsewhere, and especially to the case of Isaiah Oggins.
Meier, Andrew.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2010.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
David Dallin papers, Hoover Institution Archives
John Hook papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Herbert Solow papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Sam Tanenhaus papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical/Historical Note
1985 B.A., Wesleyan University
1989 B.A. (M.A.), Russian Language and Literature, Oxford University
1989-1992 Freelance writer
1989-Present Contributor to periodicals, including Harper's, New Republic, New York Times Magazine, National Geographic, Orion, Outside, Washington Post, Wired, and Time
1995-1996 Contributor, Pacific News Service, San Francisco, California
1996 Reported from Afghanistan
1996-2001 Moscow correspondent, Time magazine
2001-2002 Fellow, Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars, Washington, D.C.
circa 2003-Present Writer in residence, Assistant Professor at Eugene Lang College, New York, New York
2003 Author, Black Earth: A Journey through Russia after the Fall (New York: W.W. Norton)
2005 Author, Chechnya: To the Heart of a Conflict (contains excerpts from Black Earth) (New York: W.W. Norton)
2008 Author, The Lost Spy: An American in Stalin's Secret Service (New York: W.W. Norton)
Honors include Mrs. Giles Whiting Foundation Fellow; Dorothy & Lewis B. Cullman Center for Writers & Scholars at the New York Public Library; National Endowment for the Humanities Fellow; Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars; Alicia Patterson Foundation Fellow
Sources:
Contemporary Authors Online, Gale, 2010. Reproduced in Biography Resource Center. Farmington Hills, Mich.: Gale, 2010. http://galenet.galegroup.com/servlet/BioRC
"Andrew Meier - Assistant Professor" Eugene Lang College Faculty. The New School for Liberal Arts. n.d. Web. 24 August 2010.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection primarily consists of research materials for Andrew Meier's book The Lost Spy: An American in Stalin's Secret Service (New York, 2008). This research material includes correspondence and notes; photocopies of correspondence and of genealogical and biographical data; photocopies of investigative, consular and other government documents; and printed matter. The bulk of the research materials directly relate to Soviet espionage in the United States and elsewhere, and especially to the case of Isaiah Oggins.
Materials of note in the collection include the detailed genealogical and biographical data Meier compiled regarding Isaiah Oggins and his family ( Oggins family related materials ) as well as Meier's detailed research on Oggins' contemporaries and incidents relating to the Communist Party in the United States. The original order of the materials has been maintained.
Oggins, Isaiah.; Espionage, Russian--United States.; Espionage, Russian.; Secret service--Soviet Union.
- Oggins family related materials, circa 1917-2005 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Consists of Meier's research specifically pertaining to Isaiah Oggins, his family, and colleagues as well as correspondence between Meier and Oggins' son Robin and Robin's correspondence regarding Isaiah. Arranged as follows: Correspondence, Family documents, and Clippings.
  - Correspondence, 2001-2005 (Folder 1)
    Includes letters to Meier and Robin Oggins related to Freedom of Information Act requests regarding his father
    - Beardsley, Tom, 2001, 2005 (Folder 1: 1)
    - Oggins, Robin, 2001-2005 (Folder 1: 2)
  - Family documents, circa 1917-2004 (Folder 1)
    Includes correspondence to Meier and Robin Oggins's correspondence related to Freedom of Information Act requests regarding his father
    - Oggins, David and Anna, 1917-2004 (Folder 1: 3)
    - Oggins family related documents, 1930-2001 (Folder 1: 4)
      Also includes Meier's notes and related correspondence
    - Oggins family related legal documents, 1919-2005 (Folder 1: 5)
    - Oggins family related copies of photographs, circa 1910s-1920s, undated (Folder 1: 6)
    - Oggins, Robin notebooks and related materials, 1922, undated (Folder 1: 7)
      Includes materials in Chinese and Russian
  - Clippings, 1992 (Folder 1)
    - Isaiah Oggins in United States press, 1992 (Folder 1: 8)
    - Isaiah Oggins in Russian press, 1992 (Folder 1: 9)
      In Russian
- Research documents by location, 1917-2007 (Box 2-4)
  Includes clippings, articles, hand written notes, and correspondence related to Meier's research, arranged by country or repository of the research materials' origin. The bulk of the materials are photocopies.
  - Berlin, Germany, 1930-2004 (Folder 1: 10-11)
  - Columbia University, 1917-2007 (Folder 2: 1-2)
    Includes related correspondence
  - Federal Bureau of Investigation, 1943-1957, 2003 (Folder 2: 3)
    Includes information regarding Nerma Oggins
  - France, 1931-2005 (Folder 2: 4)
    Includes related correspondence. In French
  - Library of Congress, circa 1920s (Folder 2: 5)
  - National Archives and Records Administration (NARA), College Park, 1922-2004 (Folder 2: 6-8)
    Includes copies of documents from the Moscow consular files, notes, and related correspondence. Includes materials in Russian
  - NARA Index Bureau, 1920-1922 (Folder 3: 1)
  - NARA, Washington, D.C., 1995-2003 (Folder 3: 2)
    Includes notes and copies of NARA finding aids
  - National Security Agency museum, "Mask Cables,", 1934-1935, undated (Folder 3: 3)
  - New York Public Library and Yale University, 1917-2005 (Folder 3: 4-8)
    Includes separate notes. Some materials in Russian
  - Russian State Military Archive (Rossiiskii gosudarstvennyi voennyi arkhiv [RGVA]) fond 18444, 1939-1940 (Folder 3: 9)
  - Switzerland, 1931-1955 (Folder 3: 10-11)
    Some documents in German and French
  - Switzerland, 1954-1956. (Folder 4: 1)
  - Yale University Archives, 1989-1990 (Folder 4: 2)
- Research documents by subject, 1917-2007 (Box 4-11)
  Contains clippings, articles, notes, and correspondence related to Meier's research, arranged by subject, author, or title. The bulk of the materials are photocopies.
  - Abakumov, Viktor, 1999 (Folder 4: 3)
  - Arcos Limited raid, 1927, undated (Folder 4: 4)
  - Art Student League, 1927-1930 (Folder 4: 5)
    Includes information regarding Irwin Shapiro and Donald McKay
  - Carutti, Efisio, 2007 (Folder 4: 6)
  - China and Japan, 1934-2006 undated (Folder 4: 7-8)
  - Communist Party of the Soviet Union, 1991 (Folder 4: 9)
    Includes materials in Russian
  - Crouch, Paul, undated (Folder 4: 10)
    Includes notes
  - Dairen, 1936 (Folder 5: 1)
  - Dallin, David papers, circa 1924-1954 (Folder 5: 2)
    Includes notes and research from the Hoover Institution Archives
  - Dallin, David papers, 1930s, undated (Folder 5: 3)
    Includes materials in Russian and research from New York Public Library
  - Dozenberg, Nicholas, 1921-2007 (Folder 5: 4)
    Includes notes and related correspondence
  - Duff, William, 2000 (Folder 5: 5)
    Includes correspondence collected by Meier
  - Ehrmann, H.M., 1924-1927, 1990s-2000s (Folder 5: 6)
  - Eisler, Gerhart, Ruth Domino, and Angela Haden-Guest, 1947-2007 (Folder 5: 7)
    Includes research notes
  - Eitingon, Motty, 1919-1988 (Folder 5: 8)
  - Foreign Relations of the United States: Diplomatic Relations, The Soviet Union 1933-1939, 1952 (Folder 5: 9)
  - Gottlieb, Edward, 1938-2004 (Folder 5: 10)
    Includes correspondence
  - Graebner, Walter, 1942 (Folder 5: 11)
    Consists of cablegrams
  - Granich, Max and Grace, 1936-1993 (Folder 5: 12)
  - Hammerstein, Kurt von, 1933-2006 (Folder 5: 13)
    Includes documents in German
  - Hein, Egon, 1941, 2005 (Folder 5: 14)
  - Hook, John, 1927-2007 (Folder 5: 15)
  - Jaffe, Philip, 1921-1943 (Folder 5: 16)
  - Josephson, Matthew and others, 1917-2005 (Folder 6: 1)
  - "The Faking of Americans" by "Karl,", undated (Folder 6: 2)
  - Kennan, George, 1946, 2001 (Folder 6: 3)
  - Keynes, John Maynard, undated. (Folder 6: 4)
    Includes King College's finding aid for the John Maynard Keynes papers
  - Kovno and Lithuania, 1909-2002 (Folder 6: 5)
  - Krebs/Valtin, 1939-1983 (Folder 6: 6)
  - Krivitsky, Walter G., 1939-2005 (Folder 6: 7-9)
  - Lengyel, Tanja, 2000 (Folder 6: 10)
    Includes correspondence in Hungarian [?]
  - Lewis, James, 1942-2001 (Folder 6: 11)
  - Litton, Frederick S. articles, 1994-2001 (Folder 6: 12)
  - The Lusk Committee, 1992-2002. (Folder 6: 13)
    Includes finding aids and background information regarding the Lusk Committee, formally known as the Joint Legislative Committee to Investigate Seditious Activities, 1919-1920
  - The Lusk Committee, 1916-2005 (Folder 7: 1-5)
    Includes information regarding the Rand School
  - Maironski, 1993-2005 (Folder 7: 6)
  - Martin, Charles, and Steinberg, Max, 1931-2007 (Folder 7: 7)
    Includes correspondence and documents in French and Russian
  - McCargar, James interview, 1995 April 18 (Folder 7: 8)
  - Mink, George, 1935-1945 (Folder 7: 9)
  - Naito-Uchimura, Misao, circa 1990s-2001, undated (Folder 8: 1)
  - Narodnyy Komissariat Vnutrennikh Del (People's Commissariat for Internal Affairs), 1939 (Folder 8: 2)
  - Nearing, Scott, 1915-1989 (Folder 8: 3-4)
  - New York Times, 1922-2003 (Folder 8: 5)
  - Norilsk, 2005 (Folder 8: 6)
  - Rakov brothers, 1927-1996 (Folder 8: 7-10)
    Includes documents in German and Russian as well as notes by Markus Wehner regarding the Rakov brothers
  - Rand School, 1919-2005 (Folder 8: 11)
    Includes correspondence, materials generated by the Rand School and materials regarding the Rand School
  - Rand School, "A History of the Rand School of Social Science, 1906-1956" by Frederic Cornell, 1976 (Folder 9: 1)
    Master's thesis for New York University
  - Robinson case, 1938, undated (Folder 9: 2)
  - Rosenberg, Arthur, undated (Folder 9: 3)
  - Rossi, Jacques, 1979-2002 (Folder 9: 4)
    Includes some materials in French
  - The Rote Kapelle: The CIA's History of Soviet Intelligence and Espionage Networks in Western Europe, 1936-1945, 1979 (Folder 9: 5)
  - Shanghai Municipal Police file, 1933 (Folder 9: 6)
  - Shapiro, Irwin, 1931-2006 (Folder 9: 7)
    Includes notes and correspondence
  - Snow, Walter, 1981 (Folder 9: 8)
  - Solow, Herbert, circa 1937-2003, undated (Folder 9: 9-11)
  - Stevens and others, 1951-2005 (Folder 9: 12)
    Includes correspondence and notes
  - Sudoplatov, Pavel Anatol'evich, 1997-2004, undated (Folder 9: 13)
    Includes notes and documents in Russian
  - Svobodnaia mysl', 1998 (Folder 10: 1)
  - Tanenhaus, Sam, 1929-1992, undated (Folder 10: 2-5)
    Includes notes and some documents in Russian
  - Task Force on Russia documents, 1937-2007 (Folder 10: 6)
  - Wallenberg, Raoul, 1946, 2001 (Folder 11: 1)
  - Weinstein, Allen, "The Hiss Labyrinth: Seven Profiles,", 1997 (Folder 11: 2)
  - Whitney, Richard Merrill, 1924 (Folder 11: 3)
  - The Worker and other related documents, 1922-1940 (Folder 11: 4)
    The Worker includes articles written by Nerma Berman, Isaiah Oggin's wife
  - World Tomorrow,1920, undated (Folder 11: 5)
- Oversize file, 1940, undated (Box 12)
  Includes a map of Berlin and photocopied research material regarding Walter G. Krivitsky from 1940.
  - Map of Berlin, undated (Folder 12: 1)
  - Krivitsky, Walter G., related materials, 1940 (Folder 12: 1)
- Incremental materials (Box 12-15)